<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Nairobi LUG</title><link>https://nairobilug.or.ke/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/feeds/alois-mbutura.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2015 16:30:00 +0300</lastBuildDate><item><title>Meetup Summary (February, 2015)</title><link>https://nairobilug.or.ke/2015/02/meetup-february-2015.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Twenty people showed up, and as always some people were late, others were not. A few new people (ahem, Frank!), and others not as new whom I had not seen for a while. Big special shoutout to Maureiq, the only female member in the meetup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;As it happened, insider info&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was talk that everyone should try to watch the movie &lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4044364"&gt;Citizenfour&lt;/a&gt; -- an eye opening documentary on privacy, surveillance and obviously the bigger picture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jason talked of making an open source platform -- ma3map &lt;a href="https://github.com/ma3map/ma3map-client_android"&gt;client&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/ma3map/ma3map-server"&gt;server&lt;/a&gt; -- for doing route interconnection and using machine learning to decide how to effectively recommend which matatus to take (and in which order).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alan mentioned that the reason that Mozilla Firefox (or any other browser) has been so slow in the last few years is &lt;a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/nnethercote/2014/05/14/adblock-pluss-effect-on-firefoxs-memory-usage"&gt;likely due to everyone using the AdBlock Plus add-on&lt;/a&gt;, and suggested people switch to &lt;a href="https://github.com/gorhill/uBlock"&gt;µBlock&lt;/a&gt;. µBlock uses up to &lt;a href="https://github.com/gorhill/uBlock/wiki/%C2%B5Block-vs.-ABP:-efficiency-compared"&gt;two or three times less RAM&lt;/a&gt; than AdBlock Plus on both Firefox and Chrome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lots of other questions, laughs and more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my first time posting so if I may have ommitted anything important, feel free to alter my &lt;a href="https://github.com/nairobilug/nairobilug.or.ke"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; and then make a pull request. Big thanks to all the people who taught me &lt;a href="https://github.com/adam-p/markdown-here/wiki/Markdown-Here-Cheatsheet#links"&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt;... without which this post wouldn't have been possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Next time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you all on March 7th. Meetups are usually on the first Saturday of every month at KFC, Kimathi street at 16:30. Bring a friend!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Alois Mbutura</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2015 16:30:00 +0300</pubDate><guid>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2015-02-07:2015/02/meetup-february-2015.html</guid><category>KFC</category><category>meetup</category></item></channel></rss>