<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Nairobi LUG</title><link>https://nairobilug.or.ke/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/feeds/jason-rogena.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 17:25:00 +0300</lastBuildDate><item><title>Meetup Summary (May, 2015)</title><link>https://nairobilug.or.ke/2015/05/meetup-may-2015.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Just like most months, we had the monthly meetup at KFC Kimathi on the first Saturday (2nd May). Eight people showed up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Topics Discussed&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot was discussed. Opera Mini, and whether the Nairobi LUG blog should be accessible using this browser, Search Engine Optimization, learning Rust.. I'm not going to pretend I remember everything that was discussed, partly because I'm writing this one week later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;GPL Violation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One topic that was discussed that I feel like I need to highlight is the &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html"&gt;GPL&lt;/a&gt; and how some Kenyan companies are violating it. &lt;a href="https://www.brck.com/"&gt;BRCK&lt;/a&gt;, for instance, runs a fork of &lt;a href="https://openwrt.org/"&gt;OpenWRT&lt;/a&gt; yet NONE of its code is open (at least the forked OpenWRT code should be). OpenWRT is a GNU Linux distribution that comprises of at least two high profile projects (the &lt;a href="https://kernel.org/"&gt;Linux kernel&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.busybox.net/"&gt;BusyBox&lt;/a&gt;) that are licensed under the GPL. All projects that are derivatives of OpenWRT therefore are technically licensed under the GPL. I reached out to the BRCK team but I still haven't gotten a response from them. It's time 'they' know we are not fine with them violating the GPL!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VIVA GPL!!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason Rogena</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 17:25:00 +0300</pubDate><guid>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2015-05-10:2015/05/meetup-may-2015.html</guid><category>KFC</category><category>meetup</category></item><item><title>Meetup Summary (August, 2014)</title><link>https://nairobilug.or.ke/2014/08/meetup-august-2014.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;12 guys showed up, most well after 4PM. Congrats to Muya for being the only one to make it on time. The meetup was just as exciting, at least for me, as most of previous meetups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Highlights:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was a suggestion that the LUG should build a portable 'blood-glucose measuring device that plugs into a phone's audio jack' (I'm sure there's a shorter name for that) as a collaborative project, given the talent in the LUG.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was some discussion on WebRTC and its apparent bright future. Somebody even created a group for the LUG on [talky] (https://talky.io/nairobilug). No nudity please ;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No females were present in the meetup. We seriously need to get nerdy girls to come to the meetups. ~~I think~~ I'm certain there are cool girls out there... somewhere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leave comments down below and if I've left anything, feel free to make a pull request.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Pictures from Google+&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picture courtesy of Mungai&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Drinks" src="/images/meetup-august-2014.jpg" title="Nairobi GNU/Linux Users Group members" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;September Meetup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nairobi LUG meets every first Saturday of the month. The next meetup will therefore be on the 7th of September. Can't wait :)&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason Rogena</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2014 16:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2014-08-02:2014/08/meetup-august-2014.html</guid><category>KFC</category><category>meetup</category></item></channel></rss>