<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Nairobi GNU/Linux Users Group</title><link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/feeds/meetups.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://nairobilug.or.ke/</id><updated>2016-10-03T11:30:00+03:00</updated><entry><title>Meetup Summary (October, 2016)</title><link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2016/10/meetup-october-2016.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-03T11:30:00+03:00</published><updated>2016-10-03T11:30:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Frederick Muriithi</name></author><id>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2016-10-03:2016/10/meetup-october-2016.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Linux User Group is still going strong, despite the various instances that people may have mused that it is dying. The attendance was something to be proud of, and in the spirit of that, this article shall have multiple authors, to reflect the various things that were spoken about in the various enclaves that rose up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Growth Pains&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a discussion on the next step that the LUG needs to take. The question was poised to zipper: "You are at a gathering of sorts (conference, summit, etc.) and they introduce you, 'Ladies and gentlemen, today we have among us [zipper's real name] from nairobilug, to tell us who/what nairobilug is and what they do.' Go!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hilarity ensued!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of us, were able to indicate what exactly we do, besides 'meeting and having fun'. Sure, we discuss Open-Source Software, the current shenanigans the government, politicians, local institutions and businesses are up to. We even hustled &lt;a href="https://www.brck.com/"&gt;BRCK&lt;/a&gt; a &lt;a href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2015/05/brck-violating-gpl.html"&gt;while back&lt;/a&gt; and got them to come out and explain themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also gave us one BRCK for our examination, and an agreement was reached that we would do a writeup on the same. This writeup, is non-existent to-date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next issue raise to illustrate the point was the recent, IT Practitioners bill that was being debated in parliament. The question was asked, why it is the LUG was not asked for its opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conclusion was, we, as the LUG, are invisible, and a non-issue in the running of tech, and anything related, since we have not shown ourselves worthy of it. We can spend time bitching and moaning about &lt;a href="http://ihub.co.ke/"&gt;iHub&lt;/a&gt; and other tech-related groupings, companies, etc, but we have not shown another way of doing it, correct or otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was thus proposed to figure out what it is we can do as a group, that is useful to the general public in the country, so that we can grow, as a group, and also, so that we can even be taken seriously in the tech community in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Leave Your Devs Alone&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An instance came up, where a member handed in a resignation letter to the management, due to the way they kept getting interrupted at work every few minutes over mundane and inane concerns. The resignation letter was a wake-up call to the management, who have since reformed, and the whole saga had a fairy-tale ending (did it?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been written about previously, by many, more prominent developers and CEOs, that this should not be happening in 2016, but it still is...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="meetup"></category></entry><entry><title>Meetup Summary (October, 2015)</title><link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2015/10/meetup-october-2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-10-03T23:18:00+03:00</published><updated>2015-10-03T23:18:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alan Orth</name></author><id>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2015-10-03:2015/10/meetup-october-2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today's meetup was a collabo between the Nairobi LUG and Tunapanda, and it might go down in history as the most successful meeting of the Nairobi GNU/Linux Users Group &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt;. Our organizations are incredibly compatible and I'm not sure why we don't do this more often! The &lt;abbr title="Linux Users Group"&gt;LUG&lt;/abbr&gt; and Tunapanda are both forces for openness and community in Kenya. Note to self: suggest this style of meetup more often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tunapanda&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.tunapanda.org/"&gt;Tunapanda&lt;/a&gt; is a community-based organization teaching digital technology in Nairobi's Kibera estate. A few weeks ago they floated the idea of holding our next meetup at their institute and I'm grateful they did. We saw their Linux-based thin client setup, where people were working with GIMP and Blender when we walked in, and had some great conversations with students, teachers, and even the people selling beans and chapati around the corner!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other Goings Ons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always there were many other goings ons. Sometimes we talk about free, libre, open-source software, but other times we talk about life, the universe, and everything!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reducing render times in Blender by using smaller frame sizes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quite a bit of discussion about DNA sequencing, genome assembly, and the role of Linux-based systems to life sciences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3D printing &lt;a href="https://github.com/Xyl2k/TSA-Travel-Sentry-master-keys"&gt;TSA master keys&lt;/a&gt;, and how GitHub can now display 3D models in WebGL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introducing more people to IRC, for example the &lt;a href="https://kiwiirc.com/client/irc.freenode.net/#nairobilug"&gt;#nairobilug channel on Freenode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Side projects of the LUG, like the semi-defunct &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/group/show/114053-nairobi-gnu-linux-users-group"&gt;book club&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The fairly awesome quad-core ARMv7 virtual private servers from &lt;a href="http://scaleway.com/"&gt;Scaleway&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sizeable contingent of the Nairobi LUG made the pilgrimage and we were received by an equally numerous Tunapanda, making the meeting at least thirty people strong!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thanks and Welcome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to thank ALL the people who came to the meetup. The next meeting will be November 7, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="tunapanda"></category><category term="meetup"></category></entry><entry><title>Meetup Summary (July, 2015)</title><link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2015/07/meetup-july-2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-07-05T23:18:00+03:00</published><updated>2015-07-05T23:18:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Muriithi Frederick Muriuki</name></author><id>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2015-07-05:2015/07/meetup-july-2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, this month, only 4 people showed up in person, but the meeting turned out still interesting. Below is a summary of the things we talked about in no particular order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Linux (duh...)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual, we spoke about Linux, giving various experiences, some of which were particularly funny. As such, I will note one such experience, which was interesting, while he was still a noob:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a common trend on forums and irc for the more experienced folk to respond to noobs with RTFM, which each of us has at one point or the other experienced. The trouble with &lt;em&gt;nixes is that &lt;code&gt;rtfm&lt;/code&gt; could for all intents and purposes, be a valid &lt;/em&gt;nix command - so, in this case, our hapless noob went ahead and typed rtfm on his terminal emulator.
As is to be expected, we laughed our heads out... still, could there be a faster way to assist our noobs?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Education in Kenya&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This topic was especially volatile, seeing as the four people who showed up were all patrons of the system. As it were, we all railed on the (perceived?) failings of our education system, especially it's insistence on papers, without actual skill acquisition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone pointed out how in his Engineering studies (in University), practicals using the lathe involved standing in a semi-circle watching the lab technician operate the device. As is expected, that was a blatant exaggeration to make a point, but it was not far from the truth in this case, seeing as most Universities in the country focus on earning money, without much focus on upgrading the equipment required for teaching the technical courses like Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone also pointed out that one of the Universities is still teaching HTML 2.0 officially in it's Computer Science Curriculum - go figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Hackathons, Conferences, etc&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a slight segway into talks about various conferences, and how in Kenya, there seems to be a dearth of information on things like venues and times. Someone suggested that the organisers might be afraid that the NairobiLUG might criticise them &lt;a href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2015/05/brck-violating-gpl.html"&gt;as it did BRCK&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We laughed that off as unlikely and quickly moved on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Computer Security&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was an anecdote to the effect that the security organs in the country might be frowning upon discussions on computer security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was also stated that a lot of banks in the country might be using ciphers that are known to be broken and vulnerable for years now, but raising that with the concerned parties is likely to land you in jail, rather than having the issue fixed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On that chilling note, we moved along swiftly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Kenic/CA Farce&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a discussion on the news in &lt;a href="http://www.nation.co.ke/news/CA-WiFi-Internet-Rules-Cybercrime/-/1056/2771118/-/mbci1a/-/index.html"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; regarding Kenic and the Communications Authority requiring registration of gadgets to access Wi-Fi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a general consensus that the people who came up with these kind of rules do not understand how the technology works, and willfully refuse to consult with and listen to those who do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this is the least attended meetup in a really long time, it turned out to be really fascinating and fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I encourage people to show up to the next meeting on 01 August, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="kfc"></category><category term="meetup"></category></entry><entry><title>Meetup Summary (June, 2015)</title><link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2015/06/meetup-june-2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-06-14T17:25:00+03:00</published><updated>2015-06-14T17:25:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alan Orth</name></author><id>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2015-06-14:2015/06/meetup-june-2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;While I never tire of general chit chat about Linux and the broader free, libre, open-source software ecosystem, it is always nice when a meetup goes beyond that. This month we were lucky to have a few new faces drop by and shake up the monotony a bit. ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tunapanda&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few teachers and trainers from the &lt;a href="http://tunapanda.org/"&gt;Tunapanda Institute&lt;/a&gt; came by and talked about their work in the community. As a bonus, they brought their &lt;a href="http://www.cubietruck.com/"&gt;CubieTruck&lt;/a&gt; single-board mini PC which is running a modified Edubuntu, and is packed with a few hundred gigs(!) of open course content. Once booted up the device creates an open Wi-Fi access point that allows anyone to access its content via a built-in web server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They've even got some of the nuts and bolts for provisioning and managing this process on &lt;a href="https://github.com/tunapanda"&gt;their GitHub account&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;BRCK&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2015/05/meetup-may-2015.html"&gt;last month's&lt;/a&gt; discussion of &lt;a href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2015/05/brck-violating-gpl.html"&gt;BRCK's GPL violation&lt;/a&gt; BRCK reached out to us and resolved things amicably. In addition to posting &lt;a href="https://www.brck.com/open-source-compliance/"&gt;source code for their BRCKv1&lt;/a&gt; a few of their people came to the meetup to talk about OpenWRT, single-board computers, and fried chicken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, we discussed the role that the community can play in getting the word about companies that are friendly to open-source hardware and software. Simple things like how to flash vanilla software for devices, where to get source code, how to set up a build environment, unbricking, teardowns, etc. In that light, BRCK has donated one BRCKv1 unit to the LUG so we can pass it around, hack on it, and write about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's an unboxing video we shot to kick things off...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="360" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/SV9qVZQcKck" width="640"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll post more when we get time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Open All teh Things&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We briefly discussed the closed-minded culture of information and data sharing in science, but how things are changing because donors who fund research — like the &lt;a href="http://www.gatesfoundation.org/"&gt;Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="http://www.usaid.gov/"&gt;United States Agency for International Development&lt;/a&gt; (USAID), the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/department-for-international-development"&gt;Department for International Development&lt;/a&gt; (DFID), etc — are calling for the results of all new research to be free and open. Even so, in April the Elsevier group of scientific journals announced their &lt;a href="https://www.elsevier.com/connect/elsevier-updates-its-policies-perspectives-and-services-on-article-sharing"&gt;new sharing policy&lt;/a&gt; which requires publications to be licensed Creative Commons, but with the restrictive no commercial (NC) and no derivatives (ND) clauses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were reminded of the late Aaron Swartz's &lt;a href="https://archive.org/stream/GuerillaOpenAccessManifesto/Goamjuly2008_djvu.txt"&gt;Guerilla Open Access Manifesto&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Until Next Time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per our schedule of meeting on the first Saturday of the month, the next meeting should be on July 4th. Until next time, wathii!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="kfc"></category><category term="meetup"></category></entry><entry><title>Meetup Summary (May, 2015)</title><link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2015/05/meetup-may-2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-05-10T17:25:00+03:00</published><updated>2015-05-10T17:25:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Jason Rogena</name></author><id>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2015-05-10:2015/05/meetup-may-2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Just like most months, we had the monthly meetup at KFC Kimathi on the first Saturday (2nd May). Eight people showed up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Topics Discussed&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot was discussed. Opera Mini, and whether the Nairobi LUG blog should be accessible using this browser, Search Engine Optimization, learning Rust.. I'm not going to pretend I remember everything that was discussed, partly because I'm writing this one week later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;GPL Violation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One topic that was discussed that I feel like I need to highlight is the &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html"&gt;GPL&lt;/a&gt; and how some Kenyan companies are violating it. &lt;a href="https://www.brck.com/"&gt;BRCK&lt;/a&gt;, for instance, runs a fork of &lt;a href="https://openwrt.org/"&gt;OpenWRT&lt;/a&gt; yet NONE of its code is open (at least the forked OpenWRT code should be). OpenWRT is a GNU Linux distribution that comprises of at least two high profile projects (the &lt;a href="https://kernel.org/"&gt;Linux kernel&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.busybox.net/"&gt;BusyBox&lt;/a&gt;) that are licensed under the GPL. All projects that are derivatives of OpenWRT therefore are technically licensed under the GPL. I reached out to the BRCK team but I still haven't gotten a response from them. It's time 'they' know we are not fine with them violating the GPL!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VIVA GPL!!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="kfc"></category><category term="meetup"></category></entry><entry><title>Ramping Up the Ethiopia LUG</title><link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2015/04/ramping-up-ethiopia-lug.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-04-25T21:01:00+03:00</published><updated>2015-04-25T21:01:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alan Orth</name></author><id>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2015-04-25:2015/04/ramping-up-ethiopia-lug.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I had the pleasure of participating in a rare meeting of the Ethiopia GNU/Linux Users Group at the &lt;a href="http://www.iceaddis.com"&gt;iceaddis&lt;/a&gt; co-working space in Addis Ababa. In all the years I've lived in Kenya, and all the times I've been to Ethiopia, I've never heard anything about Linux or open-source software groups in the community. But alas, they do exist! I enlisted the help of some friends in Addis and planned to arrange a meeting the next time I went to Ethiopia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much to my surprise the Linux Users Group has been in existence for a few years, and even has a fairly active &lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/linux-ethiopia"&gt;mailing list&lt;/a&gt; (albeit a bit off topic!). The list is active enough that, when we sent word of the meeting, several people replied stating interest and one actually showed up to the meeting!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meeting was small, short, and sweet. In addition to our one Internet person, I brought a few of my Addis friends and colleagues. Seven people taking time out of their Saturday to talk about free, libre, open-source software and community. Not a bad start!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A Good Start&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I opened the meeting by giving a brief background of the Nairobi GNU/Linux Users Group; from a few of us trading hashtags on Twitter to regular monthly meetings, an active &lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/nairobi-gnu"&gt;mailing list&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://kiwiirc.com/client/irc.freenode.net/#nairobilug"&gt;lively IRC channel&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/nairobilug/nairobilug.or.ke"&gt;democratically managed website&lt;/a&gt;, etc. On second thought it wasn't very brief, but I'm sure it was entertaining and insightful. ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We talked about some ways to ramp up the group:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Networking with other groups like &lt;a href="https://ubuntu-za.org"&gt;Ubuntu ZA&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.linux.or.ug"&gt;Uganda LUG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Different formats for users group meetings, like alternating between informal and giving presentations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raising the profile of Linux and free, libre, open-source software in Ethiopia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating a community of people with common interests who can tip each other off about job opportunities, go rafting down the Nile together, recommend books to each other, etc (seriously!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relationships with other users groups in Addis, like the &lt;a href="https://addis.meteor.com"&gt;Meteor.js group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, I drew parallels between the early days of the Nairobi GNU/Linux Users Group and the current state of the Ethiopian group in Addis. My advice was for them to create a website and draw on social media to drive users to their mailing list to keep discussions going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Eyob's GitHub Shirt&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a shoutout to Eyob, who saw the message on the mailing list and bothered to show up. I had brought a GitHub shirt with me to give out and it just seemed right to give it to him!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Eyob with his new GitHub shirt" class="img-fluid" src="https://nairobilug.or.ke/images/ramping-up-ethiopia-lug/addis-meetup-2015-04-25.jpg" title="Eyob with his new GitHub shirt"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully that's motivation for people to show up to meetings from time to time! Also, I think he might be the first one in Addis with a GitHub shirt. w00t?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Linux Users' Couches&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I joked that I'd like to be able to take a road trip from Addis to Cape Town and sleep on Linux users' couches in cities all along the way. It's a bit of an oversimplification, but the point is that we're building networks. Whether you're looking for help on your Ubuntu machine, trying to find potential employees to manage your servers, or just need a place to sleep in Pretoria, we are building networks to connect people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to everyone that came to the meeting. Stay tuned for the next one! So long, and thanks for all the ቡና!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="meetup"></category></entry><entry><title>Meetup Summary (February, 2015)</title><link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2015/02/meetup-february-2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-02-07T16:30:00+03:00</published><updated>2015-02-07T16:30:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alois Mbutura</name></author><id>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2015-02-07:2015/02/meetup-february-2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Twenty people showed up, and as always some people were late, others were not. A few new people (ahem, Frank!), and others not as new whom I had not seen for a while. Big special shoutout to Maureiq, the only female member in the meetup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;As it Happened, Insider Info&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was talk that everyone should try to watch the movie &lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4044364"&gt;Citizenfour&lt;/a&gt; -- an eye opening documentary on privacy, surveillance and obviously the bigger picture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jason talked of making an open source platform -- ma3map &lt;a href="https://github.com/ma3map/ma3map-client_android"&gt;client&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/ma3map/ma3map-server"&gt;server&lt;/a&gt; -- for doing route interconnection and using machine learning to decide how to effectively recommend which matatus to take (and in which order).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alan mentioned that the reason that Mozilla Firefox (or any other browser) has been so slow in the last few years is &lt;a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/nnethercote/2014/05/14/adblock-pluss-effect-on-firefoxs-memory-usage"&gt;likely due to everyone using the AdBlock Plus add-on&lt;/a&gt;, and suggested people switch to &lt;a href="https://github.com/gorhill/uBlock"&gt;µBlock&lt;/a&gt;. µBlock uses up to &lt;a href="https://github.com/gorhill/uBlock/wiki/%C2%B5Block-vs.-ABP:-efficiency-compared"&gt;two or three times less RAM&lt;/a&gt; than AdBlock Plus on both Firefox and Chrome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lots of other questions, laughs and more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my first time posting so if I may have ommitted anything important, feel free to alter my &lt;a href="https://github.com/nairobilug/nairobilug.or.ke"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; and then make a pull request. Big thanks to all the people who taught me &lt;a href="https://github.com/adam-p/markdown-here/wiki/Markdown-Here-Cheatsheet#links"&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt;... without which this post wouldn't have been possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Next Time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you all on March 7th. Meetups are usually on the first Saturday of every month at KFC, Kimathi street at 16:30. Bring a friend!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="kfc"></category><category term="meetup"></category></entry><entry><title>Meetup Summary (January, 2015)</title><link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2015/01/meetup-january-2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-01-19T20:40:00+03:00</published><updated>2015-01-19T20:40:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Njagi Mwaniki</name></author><id>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2015-01-19:2015/01/meetup-january-2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;First off the meetup couldn't be held on the usual first Saturday of the month (4-Jan-2015) but was held on the second Satruday (11-Jan-2015) because by Kenyan culture people just aren't around Nairobi until at least the first Monday after first January. This pushing forward of the meetup was discussed in the mailing list and it was agreed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meetup was awesome. I had missed quite a number of them and so I met a lot of new faces. Almost everyone was new so I count for that as growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;XMPP: We had agreed in the mailing list that we would talk about running an XMPP server for secure communication among members. Sadly this matter wasn't discussed as much as I hope it would have been. What I got is that everyone thought it was a good thing, just that we didn't agree on a when and where the hosting would be done and the source of funding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monetizing apps in Kenya. How to make something people want to pay for and get them to pay for it. People want to see some sort of proof of concept first they don't just buy in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;poppingtonic and I talked about &lt;a href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/"&gt;SICP&lt;/a&gt; and some CS stuff, fun conversation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was a lot of catching up being friends and such things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="kfc"></category><category term="meetup"></category></entry><entry><title>Meetup Summary (August, 2014)</title><link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2014/08/meetup-august-2014.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-08-02T16:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2014-08-02T16:00:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Jason Rogena</name></author><id>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2014-08-02:2014/08/meetup-august-2014.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;12 guys showed up, most well after 4PM. Congrats to Muya for being the only one to make it on time. The meetup was just as exciting, at least for me, as most of previous meetups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Highlights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was a suggestion that the LUG should build a portable 'blood-glucose measuring device that plugs into a phone's audio jack' (I'm sure there's a shorter name for that) as a collaborative project, given the talent in the LUG.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was some discussion on WebRTC and its apparent bright future. Somebody even created a group for the LUG on &lt;a href="https://talky.io/nairobilug"&gt;talky&lt;/a&gt;. No nudity please ;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No females were present in the meetup. We seriously need to get nerdy girls to come to the meetups. ~~I think~~ I'm certain there are cool girls out there... somewhere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leave comments down below and if I've left anything, feel free to make a pull request.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Pictures from Google+&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picture courtesy of Mungai&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Drinks" class="img-fluid" src="https://nairobilug.or.ke/images/meetup-august-2014/meetup-august-2014.jpg" title="Nairobi GNU/Linux Users Group members"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;September Meetup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nairobi LUG meets every first Saturday of the month. The next meetup will therefore be on the 7th of September. Can't wait :)&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="kfc"></category><category term="meetup"></category></entry><entry><title>Meetup Summary (March, 2014)</title><link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2014/03/meetup-march-2014.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-03-02T21:01:00+03:00</published><updated>2014-03-02T21:01:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alan Orth</name></author><id>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2014-03-02:2014/03/meetup-march-2014.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;11 or 12 people showed up, including two first-time members (hi, Ken and friend!).  Off the top of my head, the topics discussed included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Serious Stuff&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using GPG Public Keys for signing and encrypting emails (standards, terminology, motivation, etc)&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Several members have, in the last weeks, set up and exchanged keys&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scheduling a key-signing party where attendees bring their photo IDs and GPG public key IDs so people can verify that their real identity matches their GPG identity on the GPG Public Key Infrastructure and then "sign" eachother's keys&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could be Saturday, March 8th?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need to make a push to educate people (via blog post?) so they are prepared for the party (don't come with laptops or expecting to create/publish keys!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scheduling a second, more formal LUG meetup every month; perhaps seminars or "lightning" talks&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The idea would be to give people a forum to share technical things they're doing, and let people practice public speaking skills etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Venue should be somewhere in tao to make it easy for people to be on time, possibly University of Nairobi library (with KENET connections?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perhaps could be the 3rd Saturday of the month&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Not-so-Serious Stuff&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Progress of the current Nairobi GNU/Linux Users Group book club book, Stephen King's &lt;em&gt;The Stand&lt;/em&gt;.  sticky and sentinelprime are ~50% through, but emk and raywan haven't started&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;emk's gangsta beard will rival that of Rick Ross soon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proper pronunciation of "Linux" (&lt;a href="http://safalra.com/science/linguistics/linux-pronunciation/"&gt;Linus says "Lih-nux"&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wat?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proper pronunciation of "doge"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proof that it happened:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Group shot" class="img-fluid" src="https://nairobilug.or.ke/images/meetup-march-2014/meetup-march-2014.jpg" title="Nairobi GNU/Linux Users Group members"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you for the next meeting (April 5th, 2014!)&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="kfc"></category><category term="meetup"></category></entry><entry><title>Meetup Summary (February, 2014)</title><link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2014/02/meetup-february-2014.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-02-06T16:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2014-02-06T16:00:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Njagi Mwaniki</name></author><id>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2014-02-06:2014/02/meetup-february-2014.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;16 guys showed up (staggered). I had a friend attend for the first time and he liked it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3D Printer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well great news guys have decided to build a 3D printer. Updates on that will be blogged about sooner than later I hope. I for one are very excited that we're doing such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;emk Breaks opSec&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So he decided to show up after hiding for a very very long while. He wanted it noted that he refrained from kicking zipper's teeth in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has a gangsta beard which was totally unexpected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Stuff&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was talk of getting devices into the country as a group with eebrah fascilitating that. This was very exciting since it would bring prices down for most things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;r0ckwilda{-_-} shared some interesting things he is doing with blender. I can't wait to see how that goes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sadly this time I didn't get a chance to hear Karibe talk about Physics and electronics. I always look forward to those that's for sure. You can't beat having a physicist around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oh plus everyone is talking about a book called the stand. It's really big and that just makes everyone love it haha I kid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The absence of theBOFH was noted with great concern.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I noted that there wasn't much talk/argument on distros. I always like those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some cool pics from the event that was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Group shot0" class="img-fluid" src="https://nairobilug.or.ke/images/meetup-february-2014/meetup-february-2014-0.jpg" title="Nairobi GNU/Linux Users Group members"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Group shot1" class="img-fluid" src="https://nairobilug.or.ke/images/meetup-february-2014/meetup-february-2014-1.jpg" title="Nairobi GNU/Linux Users Group members"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guys had a great time. See you at KFC Kimathi Street on March 1st, 2014. Happy hacking!!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="kfc"></category><category term="meetup"></category></entry><entry><title>Meetup Summary (January, 2014)</title><link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2014/01/meetup-january-2014.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-11T16:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2014-01-11T16:00:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alan Orth</name></author><id>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2014-01-11:2014/01/meetup-january-2014.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A major highlight of the January, 2014 meetup was having sixteen people show up (a new record!).  Other than that, there were lots of lively discussions of technology goings ons, releases, politics etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Some Topic Highlights (From Memory):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The debate over Debian voting to replace SysV Init with either &lt;a href="http://slashdot.org/story/13/10/28/1621219/debian-to-replace-sysvinit-switch-to-systemd-or-upstart"&gt;Upstart or systemd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using GPG for both signatures and encryption of email, and how to manage keychains on multiple computers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I missed anything, leave it in the comments (or send a pull request ;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Proof We Were There&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussing all teh things...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Group shot" class="img-fluid" src="https://nairobilug.or.ke/images/meetup-january-2014/meetup-january-2014.jpg" title="Nairobi GNU/Linux Users Group members"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;February Meetup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, we meet the first Saturday of the month, meaning February's meetup should be February 7th.  See you there!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="kfc"></category><category term="meetup"></category></entry><entry><title>Meetup Summary (November, 2013)</title><link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2013/11/meetup-november-2013.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-11-02T22:33:00+03:00</published><updated>2013-11-02T22:33:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Alan Orth</name></author><id>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2013-11-02:2013/11/meetup-november-2013.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A major highlight of the November, 2013 meetup was having fourteen people show up; this was perhaps the most successful meetup since we began in 2012... Other than that, there were lots of lively discussions of technology goings ons, releases, politics etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Some Topic Highlights (From Memory):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fedora 20 beta (and therefore final) &lt;a href="https://lists.fedoraproject.org/pipermail/devel/2013-October/190689.html"&gt;being delayed by one week&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://blogs.cisco.com/collaboration/open-source-h-264-removes-barriers-webrtc"&gt;Cisco releasing a BSD-licensed H.264 implementation&lt;/a&gt; (as well as binaries) and footing the licensing bill for users of the binary (ie, Mozilla Firefox, who &lt;a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/blog/2013/10/30/video-interoperability-on-the-web-gets-a-boost-from-ciscos-h-264-codec/"&gt;has said&lt;/a&gt; they will integrate this)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.openbsd.org/54.html"&gt;OpenBSD 5.4 release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The debate over Debian voting to replace SysV Init with either &lt;a href="http://slashdot.org/story/13/10/28/1621219/debian-to-replace-sysvinit-switch-to-systemd-or-upstart"&gt;Upstart or systemd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to best use the recently-registered &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nairobilug"&gt;@nairobilug&lt;/a&gt; twitter account&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How POSIX is limiting innovation (and the creep of "Linux-isms" into POSIX)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RAID vs JBOD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;telnet&lt;/code&gt; as a TCP/IP swiss army knife&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Processes vs threads&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The epic ending of last month's Nairobi GNU/Linux Users Group book club book, &lt;em&gt;The Picture of Dorian Gray&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The possibility of going whitewater rafting in Uganda in December (as the Nairobi GNU/Linux Users Group "Outdoor Explorers", a related, but unofficial affiliate of the LUG)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I missed anything, leave it in the comments (or send a pull request ;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Proof We Were There&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussing all teh things...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Group shot" class="img-fluid" src="https://nairobilug.or.ke/images/meetup-november-2013/meetup-november-2013.jpg" title="Nairobi GNU/Linux Users Group members"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;December Meetup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, we meet the first Saturday of the month, meaning December's meetup should be December 7th.  See you there!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="kfc"></category><category term="meetup"></category></entry><entry><title>Meetup Summary (October, 2015)</title><link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2013/10/october-nairobilug-meetup.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-10-02T12:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2013-10-02T12:00:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Mwaoshe Njemah</name></author><id>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2013-10-02:2013/10/october-nairobilug-meetup.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We will be holding our October GNU/Linux User Group Meetup on 5th October between 04.00 – 06.00 pm EAT (GMT +3) at KFC Kimathi Street. We traditionally meet the first Saturday of every month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Speakers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have this crazy format where everyone gets to speak! We talk about what we are doing with Linux and happenings in the FOSS scene locally and beyond in the past month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;RSVP&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please RSVP for the event on Google+  and join us in person at KFC or via IRC Chat (between 04.00 – 06.00 pm EAT (GMT +3))&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google Group and Mailing List&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/group/nairobi-gnu"&gt;groups.google.com/group/nairobi-gnu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IRC Channel&lt;/strong&gt; #nairobilug @ freenode&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For non-IRC users: &lt;a href="http://webchat.freenode.net/?channels=nairobilug"&gt;webchat.freenode.net/?channels=nairobilug&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="meetup"></category><category term="kfc"></category></entry></feed>