<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Nairobi LUG</title><link>https://nairobilug.or.ke/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/feeds/muriithi-frederick-muriuki.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 23:18:00 +0300</lastBuildDate><item><title>Meetup Summary (July, 2015)</title><link>https://nairobilug.or.ke/2015/07/meetup-july-2015.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;So, this month, only 4 people showed up in person, but the meeting turned out still interesting. Below is a summary of the things we talked about in no particular order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Linux (duh...)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual, we spoke about Linux, giving various experiences, some of which were particularly funny. As such, I will note one such experience, which was interesting, while he was still a noob:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a common trend on forums and irc for the more experienced folk to respond to noobs with RTFM, which each of us has at one point or the other experienced. The trouble with &lt;em&gt;nixes is that &lt;code&gt;rtfm&lt;/code&gt; could for all intents and purposes, be a valid &lt;/em&gt;nix command - so, in this case, our hapless noob went ahead and typed rtfm on his terminal emulator.
As is to be expected, we laughed our heads out... still, could there be a faster way to assist our noobs?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Education in Kenya&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This topic was especially volatile, seeing as the four people who showed up were all patrons of the system. As it were, we all railed on the (perceived?) failings of our education system, especially it's insistence on papers, without actual skill acquisition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone pointed out how in his Engineering studies (in University), practicals using the lathe involved standing in a semi-circle watching the lab technician operate the device. As is expected, that was a blatant exaggeration to make a point, but it was not far from the truth in this case, seeing as most Universities in the country focus on earning money, without much focus on upgrading the equipment required for teaching the technical courses like Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone also pointed out that one of the Universities is still teaching HTML 2.0 officially in it's Computer Science Curriculum - go figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Hackathons, Conferences, etc&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a slight segway into talks about various conferences, and how in Kenya, there seems to be a dearth of information on things like venues and times. Someone suggested that the organisers might be afraid that the NairobiLUG might criticise them &lt;a href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/2015/05/brck-violating-gpl.html"&gt;as it did BRCK&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We laughed that off as unlikely and quickly moved on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Computer Security&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was an anecdote to the effect that the security organs in the country might be frowning upon discussions on computer security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was also stated that a lot of banks in the country might be using ciphers that are known to be broken and vulnerable for years now, but raising that with the concerned parties is likely to land you in jail, rather than having the issue fixed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On that chilling note, we moved along swiftly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Kenic/CA Farce&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a discussion on the news in &lt;a href="http://www.nation.co.ke/news/CA-WiFi-Internet-Rules-Cybercrime/-/1056/2771118/-/mbci1a/-/index.html"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; regarding Kenic and the Communications Authority requiring registration of gadgets to access Wi-Fi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a general consensus that the people who came up with these kind of rules do not understand how the technology works, and willfully refuse to consult with and listen to those who do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this is the least attended meetup in a really long time, it turned out to be really fascinating and fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I encourage people to show up to the next meeting on 01 August, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Muriithi Frederick Muriuki</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 23:18:00 +0300</pubDate><guid>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2015-07-05:2015/07/meetup-july-2015.html</guid><category>KFC</category><category>meetup</category></item><item><title>Installing Debian Jessie on the Acer C710-2833 Chromebook</title><link>https://nairobilug.or.ke/2014/03/installing-debian-jessie-on-the-acer-c710-2833-chromebook.html</link><description>&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have recently had need to get a machine for work that is easy to lug around, affordable and has a decent battery life. While I already have a laptop (Presario CQ62), it has grown old and its battery life is in the shitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After shopping around, I settled for the Acer C710-2833 Chromebook (I would have picked a newer model, but there is not one in our market yet, and importing one would have made it quickly unaffordable - thank the new government).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, while Chrome OS - the operating system that comes with the machines - is a nice (great?) operating system, for a freelance developer like me, it renders the machine useless for much of my day to day work. I found the need therefore to make it useful for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DISCLAIMER&lt;/strong&gt;: FROM THIS POINT FORWARD, ANYTHING YOU DO WITH YOUR MACHINE IS YOUR FAULT. IF IT BREAKS, OR YOU BRICK IT, OR CAUSE A NUCLEAR HOLOCAUST, OR ANYTHING ELSE FOR THAT MATTER, YOU CAN ONLY BLAME YOURSELF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that that is out of the way, shall we proceed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, let us start with where you can acquire the machine in Kenya. I got my machine at Ebrahim Electronics Limited along Kimathi Street. The machine costs a whooping Kshs 19,000. Also, do not forget to carry the manuals with you like I did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would recommend you also get yourself a flash-disk at this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now you have your spanking new machine. Make sure to claim your free 100GB storage on google drive before you proceed. Also, BACKUP any user data you might have put on the machine&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reading Material&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process that is involved is tricky, and while I try to give a roadmap, I will not give the instructions, rather, I will point to the various resources I found useful&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SERIOUSLY, DO NOT JUST JUMP IN AND START COPYING AND PASTING COMMANDS! YOU WILL BRICK YOUR MACHINE. YOU HAVE BEEN WARNED.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Getting to Developer Mode&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chromebooks have two modes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Normal user mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developer mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href="http://www.chromium.org/chromium-os/chromiumos-design-docs/developer-mode"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.chromium.org/chromium-os/developer-information-for-chrome-os-devices/acer-c7-chromebook"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; for more information on developer mode&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;CoreBoot&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These links are about coreboot. PLEASE READ THROUGH THEM A COUPLE OF TIMES before attempting anything
For an introduction to coreboot see &lt;a href="https://johnlewis.ie/mediawiki/index.php?title=Coreboot_on_Chromebooks"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://johnlewis.ie/coreboot-on-chromebooks/pre-built-firmware/"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; you can find a list of the existing coreboot firmware. DO NOT RUSH JUST YET. Read on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Getting the ISO&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now need to download an iso image to use as the installation source. It is important that you research and figure out what processor your machine uses. For the C710-2833, it uses the &lt;a href="http://ark.intel.com/products/56056/Intel-Celeron-Processor-847-2M-Cache-1_10-GHz"&gt;Intel Celeron 847&lt;/a&gt;. This is an x86_64 architecture, otherwise known as amd64.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Armed with that knowledge, get to &lt;a href="http://www.debian.org/"&gt;http://www.debian.org&lt;/a&gt; and get the relevant image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this time, it is recommended that you get Debian Jessie &lt;a href="http://www.debian.org/devel/debian-installer/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ready To Go&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, you have read up on coreboot, you have the image all that remains is the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start off &lt;a href="https://wiki.debian.org/InstallingDebianOn/Acer/C710-2615-Chromebook"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; - you will get some information on the current status of your machine. It is also where you will finish your journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have read through that at least twice, now start the actual installation. The process to follow is &lt;a href="https://johnlewis.ie/mediawiki/index.php?title=Flashing_stock_firmware_to_a_coreboot_build_on_Acer_C7_%28C710%29"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the core boot, I used the 'Grub2 for Intel Celeron 847' with an md5 sum of &lt;code&gt;9c5993518ddf97ab4c4cf7e0a2f84570&lt;/code&gt;. I picked it because I have used grub2 before and felt comfortable starting off in a farmiliar place. You are welcome to try a different one if you know what you are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you follow the instructions carefully, you should get through without problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Finally&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you have Debian on your system, it is time to do the post-installation steps. As I told you, those are found on the page you &lt;a href="https://wiki.debian.org/InstallingDebianOn/Acer/C710-2615-Chromebook"&gt;started off with&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great! Now go ye and be productive!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;EDITS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;April 21, 2014: Sometimes the trackpad does not work - to correct that, you could do the following (from &lt;a href="http://marstella.net/?p=278"&gt;marstella.net&lt;/a&gt; also, thanks to eebrah)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edit &lt;code&gt;/etc/modprobe.d/blacklist.conf&lt;/code&gt; and include the following line&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;blacklist chromeos_laptop
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edit &lt;code&gt;/etc/modules&lt;/code&gt; and include the following lines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;i2c-i801
i2c-dev
chromeos_laptop
cyapa
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Muriithi Frederick Muriuki</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2014 19:15:00 +0300</pubDate><guid>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2014-03-19:2014/03/installing-debian-jessie-on-the-acer-c710-2833-chromebook.html</guid><category>hardware</category><category>Chromebook</category><category>Debian</category></item><item><title>Scars in Web App Trenches</title><link>https://nairobilug.or.ke/2014/02/scars-in-web-app-trenches.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Hey there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been developing web applications for a while now, working freelance on oDesk, and from my work, I can state I do have some experience in doing this. Now, I will not claim to be a web-app ninja, but I will try to state my case as objectively as I can, but you decide how much salt you'll take it with. Deal?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;HTML - The M is for Markup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From what I have come to understand from the gurus and ninjas in this field, HTML was built as a markup language. It was meant to give meaning to the content of the page, e.g.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;lt; h1 &amp;gt; is greater than &amp;lt; h2 &amp;gt;, which in turn is greater than &amp;lt; h3 &amp;gt; etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;lt; form &amp;gt; represents an electronic form where you can fill in and submit data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;lt; button &amp;gt; and &amp;lt; input type='button' ... &amp;gt; represent input elements that can be used to activate certain actions like submit forms, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;lt; a &amp;gt; - the anchor tag, is meant to represent links to a different part of the page, other pages, or another site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and many others. . . (For awesome HTML, CSS and Javascript tutorials, click &lt;a href="http://htmldog.com/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if there is one thing that I have found painful in my work, it is when people make use on the anchor tag to submit forms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am one of those people still living in a third world country (and if things keep going the way they are, we just might have to come up with a whole new class beneath that for the country), and as such, bandwidth is expensive (I dare say, artificially so).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, we all know that the tag &amp;lt; input type='submit' ... &amp;gt; will submit any form it is in, no questions asked, but 'NOOOOOOOOO!', we have to bloat that up by getting rid of it, replacing it with a link, and then using the jQuery library to submit the form. A form submission, I tell you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;But The Web is Javascript!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all that have this argument, I refer you &lt;a href="http://motherfuckingwebsite.com/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Now, tell me you cannot see the content in that site. Then, riddle me this, before Javascript, jQuery, and others came along, pray tell, how were people submitting their html forms?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now understand this &lt;strong&gt;I love Javascript&lt;/strong&gt; and though I am not a jQuery ninja, I cannot argue against it's merits, but if we are going to use javascript everywhere, we might as well start killing mosquitoes with handguns, or slings, or catapults (take your pick).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Back to the Basics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hear me out, before you fetch the noose. I am making a simple suggestion here, based on the experience I have had with web applications, and even some plain websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I land on your site, almost always, I am searching for information about your company, skill, etc. You, on the other hand, decide to make me have to struggle further to find the friggin content by putting those silly pictures, animations and shiznit in my path. Then, to insult me further, you make it so that, if I turn javascript off (It's off by default on my browser), I cannot see your content.
As if you have not hurt me enough, you make all your forms submit only via javascript/jQuery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DEAR &lt;deity&gt;! I cannot count the number of times I have left websites and gone looking for other options due to this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you eat away my bandwidth with silly content, then you force me to use even more of my bandwidth, just to get functionality that is already built into html.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Collaboration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us view another scenario. You have to collaborate with a person in a different timezone building a web application. Now, you are a javascript, jQuery, etc ninja, and you can build anything in it. Her/him, not so much, but they are good at their PHP, Ruby, Python, C or whatever language they use on the backend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I do not know what you think, but I dare say, it is easier to pass to each other data, than force the backend to rely on the design of the frontend. Think also, of when you decide you want to change the look and feel of the website, then you have to make changes to both the front and backends, introducing new bugs, and possibly throwing away months of work debugging the data communication etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if you had simply passed data between the frontend and backend, say using &lt;strong&gt;json, xml, plain text, plain html&lt;/strong&gt; and others, then you can change the frontend any time without worrying about the backend, since the data interchange format is standardised, agreed upon, and &lt;strong&gt;DE&lt;/strong&gt;fucking&lt;strong&gt;BUGGED!&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The backend guy/gal, can now concentrate on building and testing the backend, even with plain, unstyled, ugly, but functional html, and you can concentrate on styling (CSS) and behaviour (Javascript), without breaking the backend every time you make a tiny little change to the front end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, think of your client, and how happy they are, every time they contact you to change the look and feel of the website, and you do that in a few weeks without breaking the backend, and they think you are a god!
Yeah, keep doing the shit you're doing, and that will never happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm angry, and so are you. Let me know what you think in the comments. Try to be civil, though I probably haven't.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Muriithi Frederick Muriuki</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2014 13:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2014-02-17:2014/02/scars-in-web-app-trenches.html</guid><category>web applications</category><category>web development</category></item><item><title>In The Spirit of Pelican</title><link>https://nairobilug.or.ke/2013/07/in-the-spirit-of-pelican.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I have to start by commending everyone involved in the Nairobi Linux User Group (nairobilug) for their various efforts to get all of us to this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, I wish to thank &lt;em&gt;Mr. Alan Orth&lt;/em&gt; for introducing us (or was it just me?) to Pelican, and providing the tutorial for getting it running. Also, for setting up the system so that we can all collaborate to add content to the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would also like to thank the visionary fellows who had the light-bulb moment to start off the &lt;em&gt;LUG&lt;/em&gt;. Here, I specifically target &lt;em&gt;nj3ma&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;eebrah&lt;/em&gt;. You spoke of it in university, but I was too busy chasing tail and the A's :D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there is all the rest of you people who saw fit to join the LUG and further light the fire. I am grateful to have met all of you in person. And for those of you I have yet to meet in person, I look forward to meeting you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;And Now, a code block&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;[aorth@noma: ~]$ uname -sr
Linux 3.9.9-1-ARCH
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;And now, a list&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could not resist doing this... here is a list of the nicks on irc as I type this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alfontefonte&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;highPriestLOL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;raywan|away&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;@eebrah|away&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr3amc0d3r_&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;karfes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;varud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;@stickyboy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fredmanglis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;r0ckwilda|away&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shout out to all of you great peoples!!!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Muriithi Frederick Muriuki</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2013 20:22:00 +0300</pubDate><guid>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2013-07-14:2013/07/in-the-spirit-of-pelican.html</guid><category>pelican</category><category>publishing</category></item></channel></rss>