<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Nairobi LUG</title><link>https://nairobilug.or.ke/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://nairobilug.or.ke/feeds/njagi-mwaniki.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2015 20:40:00 +0300</lastBuildDate><item><title>Meetup Summary (January, 2015)</title><link>https://nairobilug.or.ke/2015/01/meetup-january-2015.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;First off the meetup couldn't be held on the usual first Saturday of the month (4-Jan-2015) but was held on the second Satruday (11-Jan-2015) because by Kenyan culture people just aren't around Nairobi until at least the first Monday after first January. This pushing forward of the meetup was discussed in the mailing list and it was agreed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meetup was awesome. I had missed quite a number of them and so I met a lot of new faces. Almost everyone was new so I count for that as growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XMPP: We had agreed in the mailing list that we would talk about running an XMPP server for secure communication among members. Sadly this matter wasn't discussed as much as I hope it would have been. What I got is that everyone thought it was a good thing, just that we didn't agree on a when and where the hosting would be done and the source of funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monetizing apps in Kenya. How to make something people want to pay for and get them to pay for it. People want to see some sort of proof of concept first they don't just buy in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;poppingtonic and I talked about &lt;a href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/"&gt;SICP&lt;/a&gt; and some CS stuff, fun conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a lot of catching up being friends and such things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Njagi Mwaniki</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2015 20:40:00 +0300</pubDate><guid>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2015-01-19:2015/01/meetup-january-2015.html</guid><category>KFC</category><category>meetup</category></item><item><title>Meetup Summary (February, 2014)</title><link>https://nairobilug.or.ke/2014/02/meetup-february-2014.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;16 guys showed up (staggered).
I had a friend attend for the first time and he liked it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3D printer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well great news guys have decided to build a 3D printer. Updates on that will be blogged about sooner than later I hope. I for one are very excited that we're doing such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;emk breaks opSec&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So he decided to show up after hiding for a very very long while. He wanted it noted that he refrained from kicking zipper's teeth in. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has a gangsta beard which was totally unexpected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Stuff&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was talk of getting devices into the country as a group with eebrah fascilitating that. This was very exciting since it would bring prices down for most things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;r0ckwilda{-_-} shared some interesting things he is doing with blender. I can't wait to see how that goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly this time I didn't get a chance to hear Karibe talk about Physics and electronics. I always look forward to those that's for sure. You can't beat having a physicist around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh plus everyone is talking about a book called the stand. It's really big and that just makes everyone love it haha I kid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The absence of theBOFH was noted with great concern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I noted that there wasn't much talk/argument on distros. I always like those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some cool pics from the event that was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Group shot0" src="/images/meetup-february-2014-0.jpg" title="Nairobi GNU/Linux Users Group members" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Group shot1" src="/images/meetup-february-2014-1.jpg" title="Nairobi GNU/Linux Users Group members" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guys had a great time. See you at KFC Kimathi Street on March 1st, 2014.
Happy hacking!!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Njagi Mwaniki</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2014 16:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid>tag:nairobilug.or.ke,2014-02-06:2014/02/meetup-february-2014.html</guid><category>KFC</category><category>meetup</category></item></channel></rss>